so the question is on um
which is uh
the two types of
thought that the buddha talks about
imaginary so the gist is that the buddha realized
so the gist is that the buddha realized
that
if he were to allow thoughts of greed
aversion delusion to uh
uh to sort of uh make him act out of it
to be able to welcome them if he were to
entertain them
if he were to delight such a risen
thoughts um it would lead to his affliction the
um it would lead to his affliction the
affliction of others it would lead away
from nirvana
then consequently he realized that
if if a thought of renunciation arises
and if he were to allow it if he were to
welcome it if he were to entertain it if
he were to cultivate it
it would not lead to his affliction and
he would not lead away from nibana thus
he then started cultivating the thoughts
of renunciation
as you have to mention in other talks
it's not about getting rid
of the origin thoughts even if they're
unwholesome it's about not welcoming them
it's about not welcoming them
it's about not
not being careless in regard to their
presence while they're present
so
so in this sutra the buddha says that
as he would be abiding diligent ardent
in resolute a thought of central desire
would arise in him so
thought would arise on its own despite
him being ardent and resolute so that's
not a problem so that's not something he
needs to get rid of
in a sense of that's not something he
needs to prevent directly or he can
prevent directly from arising he can't
do that
so but when the sensual the thought of
sensual desire arose he would have he
understood thus
this thought has arisen in me leads to
my own affliction affliction of others
affliction both and so on
leads away from nibana
so this is something that
that needs to be contemplated
so the affliction for me affliction for
others affliction for both
uh it's not going to be evident
certainly not going to be self-evident
in the beginning when somebody say they
allow these thoughts to arise this
nature is still kind of hidden not seen
not understood so that's where that
diligence comes in
so while you're enduring the pressure
centrality you don't act out of it and then
you don't act out of it and then
those thoughts that are around you want
to be able to have enough space to to
start seeing their their affliction
their lack of merit their
their misfortune in that sense
misfortune in that sense
the problem is that the pressure of
sensuality is unpleasant
so what that results in is that then
people immediately want to get rid of the
immediately want to get rid of the
thoughts because of their pain and then
they contemplate their affliction and
their misery but it's all rooted in
simply trying to deny the thoughts
because they hurt you
so that's why i keep saying the thoughts
need to be endured first
so you you have to have enough strength
to have the pain of sensuality there
without clouding your reason your
judgment and so on
if you have developed somebody to that
extent then you can start actually diligently
then you can start actually diligently
uh reminding yourself clarifying further
and developing and and developing that
context of their affliction
how unbeneficial they are and so on
so
while the sensual the thought of sensual
desire was present in him
he would be considering
how the presence of this thought that
i'm under that i'm enduring that i'm not
acting out of
is actually an affliction it's actually
uh detrimental to my well-being it
actually leads away from my goal of
nibbana and while he would be uh
considering that the thought that has
arisen on its own of central desire
would subside
so that's how you get rid of those
thoughts not like i must stop this thinking
not like i must stop this thinking
so that's the point one point to note
from this suta
and then then it goes into uh
into saying that whatever beku whatever
a person frequently thinks about ponders
upon welcomes the lights revolves around that
welcomes the lights revolves around that
will become an inclination of his mind
so
if you allow your mind to frequently
think thoughts of sensuality or thoughts
of ill will or thoughts of aversion or
thoughts of resistance or sort of
carelessness that will become the
inclination to state of your mind and
the most practical terms the the
inclination of your mind
really just means
what what
what your mind would be
generally revolving around it means that
those thoughts would be then coming more
frequently because you have been
welcoming them delighting in them and so
on so the inclination of the mind
determines your susceptibility
to those those types of thoughts
and then consequently if you are
diligent and and make the effort to not
welcome such type of thoughts for a you
know sufficient amount of time
sufficient amount of time
uh then those uh the inclination of mind
will change which means then those
thoughts would be coming less and less
frequently if you frequently allow your mind to to
if you frequently allow your mind to to
think about thoughts of renunciation the
contemplating benefits during your
meditation you're going to play benefits
of giving things up
relinquishing uh letting go of
appropriations and ownership and uh and
and similar that will become the
inclination of your mind if during your
meditation you start considering
how solitude should be cultivated should be
solitude should be cultivated should be
developed should be delighted in
uh no company should be
minimized avoided
avoided
and you should basically
be learning how to live with yourself
and your own thoughts in solitude that
would become the inclination of your
mind so it's you know sometimes people might
so it's you know sometimes people might
feel like i kept i have these thoughts
keep coming up and i don't know how to
deal with them you're not supposed to
deal with the thoughts
you're supposed to recognize them the
way they arise and then see the mental
state behind them
which is basically something you are
responsible for
through prior welcoming the lighting
entertaining of such thoughts
so if those thoughts that arise
are unwholesome our pressuring are
unpleasant you consider that their
presence their arising
their arising
is not in your control
yet if you welcome that arising if you
entertain that arising you are leading
yourself away from nirvana and calming
and peace
so thus then you you dwell vigilant
that's all you can do so it's not like
yeah but what do i do then so these
thoughts disappear and they don't bother
me
that's what you do you remain vigilant
while those thoughts are here
so that they don't lead you astray and
then they will subside on their own
and then that will be peaceful and then
you recognize okay so
all i need to do as we said in in those
all those previous talks and in that
book as well is not open the door not
let them in and the similarly the buddha
gives it's like
just as in the last month of the rainy
season in autumn when the crops thicken
a cowherd would guard his cows
by constantly tapping and poking them on
this side with a stick to check and curb
them why is that because he sees that he
could be
flogged in prison find a blamed he could
get in trouble if he were to let those
cows stray into other people's crops
so if you were to let your mind welcome
delight entertain
accept other people's crops i.e the tempting
other people's crops i.e the tempting
thoughts of pressuring desire acting out
of ill will going towards distraction
those are the crops for you
and even more specifically
sight sound smell taste touches are
other people's crops that's what buddha
said so because people would take what
belongs to mara mara would then
do with them what he wants
and what are the things that belong to
moderate sight sounds smell taste
touches so a person would be taking those up
so a person would be taking those up
particularly because of the pleasures
that one gets through those things
and because of that one is enslaved by
modest control
so you can't get rid of the crops they
don't belong to you they're just there
because you know they have reason on
their own they're not your problem the
problem is you letting your mind going
there carelessly and and eating and
enjoying things that don't belong to it
and that's what gets you in trouble so
in this in this sense the the shepherd
he he realizes that all he just needs to
keep keep check on his cows
because there is a danger for him if he
lets them go astray as simple as that so
you need to keep check on yourself in
regard to the thoughts that are
presenting themselves to you
and you see the more you keep yourself
in check
the less you will be fueling
these thoughts of desire and ill will
which means less and less that would be
an inclination of your mind it will not
be as frequently an inclination of your
mind as it is maybe now
and so when those thoughts subside
so when those thoughts subside
and that's the point the buddha that
makes with a with a follow-up simile
when there are no more crops when you
know it's out of season now
so
you don't really need to guard cows how
far they go because there is no
no trouble no trap no no no no issues
that they can create because the crops
are gone
then all you need to do is be mindful
that the the cows are there
so
if you have sufficiently
endured the pressuring thoughts of other
people's crops
so the pressuring thoughts of desire
your will
sensuality distraction
guarding your mind not letting your mind
welcome delight entertain and act out i
go into the other people's crops
then the thoughts of renunciation will become
the thoughts of renunciation will become
your norm and thoughts of sensuality
will be seen as dangerous and welcoming
and it will be easier and easier to not
welcome them when thoughts of
renunciation become your norm there is
no danger
because they
you you don't you you're not you're not
acting out of desire you're not wanting
anything that doesn't belong to you so
just thoughts arise on their own and you
realize oh these thoughts of
they don't want to go into so they say
imagine you have a cow that doesn't want
to go in other people's crops and now
you know that
and now that cow listens to you
and obeys your will
so then you don't need to constantly
poke it like how you used to have to do
it how you used to have to keep it
drained in
because there is no more the same type
of pulling pressure and then all you
need to do is know that the cow is there
so don't just completely lose it out of
your side because then he might you know
decide to go somewhere where he
shouldn't so but you don't have to actively be uh
so but you don't have to actively be uh
be restraining it and keeping an eye on
it in a sense of
um it's enough for you to know
that your mind is there when it's in
when it's having a thought of
renunciation as it's known
uh and there will be enough to to
protect that uh that mind and yourself
uh from from any peril that could arise
if you give
if you give in to thoughts of sensuality
so in the same sense the simile then
continues and says the buddha says the
um so when all the crops have been
brought inside cowherd would guard his
cows whilst telling the root of a tree
but he only needs to be mindful that the
cows are there he only needed to be
mindful that his mind the state of mind
that is there nothing else
he didn't need to worry about the
thoughts because he has replaced
the the thoughts of pressuring desires
and ill will
they have subsided that's how he
replaced them they've subsided and then
became replaced by the thoughts of
renunciation um which was then seen as beneficial and
um which was then seen as beneficial and
non-dangerous so when thoughts of
renunciation are the thoughts that are arising for
are the thoughts that are arising for
you are the thoughts that you value uh
the state of mind behind that you don't
have to fear
and you don't need to protect this
closely you actually can relax within it
and that's in itself a form of samadhi
however having still those thoughts come and go
having still those thoughts come and go
on their own it's not uh
as good
of as useful of a samadhi as it would be
if you were to calm down further in
regard to those thoughts
so that's that's what the suta continues
then where the weather does yeah he can
if he were to think these thoughts
pronunciation day and night day and
night uh no affliction would rise for him or
uh no affliction would rise for him or
others there would be no basis for any
possibility of affliction to rise if
those thoughts are his mode of being
however if he were to dwell thinking
like that all the time
that would not be uh
calming overall it would probably tire
out his mind
and tiredness means he's not quite
tiredness means he's not quite
composed as well as he could be
so before we go into uh how would you
compose then uh it's actually important
to note that
this step of composing internally and
calming down
only applies
after thoughts of sensuality you will
thoughts of sensuality you will
pressure doubt the five hindrances
are not moving you anymore
it only applies after you have been
diligent ardent resolute and only having
thoughts of renunciation that revolve
around in your mind and when thoughts of
other people's crops arise they
dissipate almost instantaneously because
you have not been welcoming and
entertaining those thoughts
prior to that long enough
and just as a reminder
you have also not been trying to get rid
of those thoughts because they were
unpleasant which would have been on the
level of acting out of a version so if
you haven't been doing it long enough
they will be subsiding and being and
become less and less frequent
so the reason why i'm pointing this out
is because sometimes a person can think
yes i'm restrained
everything in totality i'm thinking
thoughts of renunciation that's good but
now i also want to not think anything
but the problem with
you sort of trying to do it as opposed
to being a natural next step that will
occur after thoughts of renunciation has
been established as your mode of being
is that uh
your attempts would be basically rooted
in still trying to get rid of the
arising of thoughts you will try to get
rid of the
that that aspect of thought coming on its own
that aspect of thought coming on its own
and bothering you in other words you
haven't quite dealt with the bothering
aspect of the thoughts which is why you
want to get rid of them through jhana
and so on vagina will come when you stop
trying to get rid of thoughts but learn
how not to be moved by them in order not
to be moved by them you need to have
thoroughly sufficiently developed
thoughts of renunciation
the benefits of renunciation the value
the peace the the non-peril
the the the non-danger all of those
values need to need to be something you
frequently reflect upon and then yes
even if you get tired on account of it
it's good tiredness it's tiredness from
a good work
the time will come when you will
recognize that now you don't even have
to do that good work anymore but until
that time comes on its own you just have
to
even if it's tiring and sometimes
unpleasant because if you try to do it sooner it's
because if you try to do it sooner it's
going to be on the level of still that
view that it would be better if i don't
have these thoughts because i still on
some level don't want to deal with the
bothering aspects and because of that
you are actually bothered and because of
that your attempts at
it's still in your mind internally
and and sort of
and sort of
surmounting the domain of thinking and
pondering in the first genre
that still has thinking and pondering
but now you're completely unbothered
well that will remain unreachable
because you still act out of craving
against thoughts
in order to to to still your mind
internally into that first jhana and
then second ghana
you need to have no craving present
so you need to have sufficiently
thoroughly not acted out of craving
not acted out of craving
um
dwelt on the on the perceptions of
danger in regard to central thoughts
thoughts of illegal thoughts of
distraction until that you know the danger of other
until that you know the danger of other
people's crops until the mind comes down
on its own not until you feel like you
wanna enter jhana now
so that's why every genre description
starts by having been withdrawn from
sensuality he experienced pleasure on account of it
he experienced pleasure on account of it
the the chitta viveka of the mind is the
viveka it's the it's the seclusion from
unwholesome states
when the mind recognizes that it's
totally secluded the joy pleasure is
born on account of it and then he enters
and abides in jhana
and we pointed it before it's not like i
do something i enter john a pleasure of
janna comes to me no no i do something
meaning i see the danger in the entire
domain of central thoughts thoughts
available thoughts of distraction the
entire domain of the five hindrances
i contemplate i work on sustaining the
perception of that danger i am not
negligent in regard to it that's how i
seclude myself from it
pleasure from of safety from those
dangerous states see you will feel safe
now if you
uh
basically if the crops have kind of been
taken away
there is no more risk there are no more
temptation for the cow you feel relieved
and that's exactly the pleasure of the
first genre relief
relief from that burden
so
you do the work in terms of seeing the
danger protect the mind from from
leaping into those thoughts of danger
then when that comes down you will
experience the relief so the pleasure
that's usually certainly the pleasure of
entering the jhana it's actually the
pleasure of withdrawal from unwholesome
states so unwholesome states gives you the
so unwholesome states gives you the
pleasure of relief
and when that pleasure of relief is is
something you become used to
that's how you enter the genres among
thinking and pondering and that's how
you can instill your mind internally
so there is no shortcut
you can't just enter the genre they will
then bypass the necessity for thoroughly
bypass the necessity for thoroughly
uh
seeing and perceiving and sustaining the
perception of danger
and affliction in thoughts of sensuality
thoughts of will and thoughts of
distraction so so that's the work so in other words
so so that's the work so in other words
you will most likely practically
speaking need to get tired first
from constant
constantly sustaining and protecting
your mind within like thoughts of
renunciation thoughts of giving up
thoughts of non-desire thoughts of
nibana up until like sensuality ill will and
up until like sensuality ill will and
and distraction doesn't pressure you as
much then
then
with that kind of new space you created
through that sort of relief you can okay
now let me let me let me uh relieve
myself further
from from the from the duty of having to
kind of sustain the thoughts of
renunciation and you will be able to
then do so because again the confidence
will come because now you see that these
thoughts of sensuality or will
are not as frequent i notice pressuring
i'm more distant like the crops are far
away so you don't need to be like every
so you don't need to be like every
second keeping an eye on whether your
cow is welcoming the idea of it and
trying to go there
but you can give them some space and
when you give them some space you learn
then just how to see the state of mind
without needing to police every single
movement of the cow
and then within that okay now let me
just calm down and sort of even drop
those cows so to speak or actually even
more accurately so
[Music] calm those cows
calm those cows
sit them down stop them from moving
because if the cows that you need to
keep an eye on
are laying down
still motionless not moving
motionless not moving
there is not even a possibility of them
going to the crops
for as long as they don't get up and
start walking around
so not even having the immediate
possibility of engaging with danger
of engaging with danger
is then even like a further form of
relief and calming down
because the the danger the temptation
has been removed sufficiently enough so
that viveka of the first ghana
seclusion from unwholesome state has
been developed sufficiently enough what
is sufficient you will not only want to
develop it you can't decide beforehand
oh this feels sufficient
it's sufficient when those thoughts are
too distant when those thoughts have
lost their power throughout eventuality
of will and distraction
it's sufficient when basically thoughts
of nirvana thoughts of renunciation
uh thoughts of giving up thoughts of
solitude provide you with pleasure
delight and that fatigue that comes on
account of them
is also something you enjoy let's put it
that way so when the buddha said that
fatigue was not not conducive for
developing samadhi developing composure
that's only relatively speaking it's not
that fatigue is not conducive
for developing that samadhi and
composure from the point of view of
ghana but it's very conducive for
developing samadhi composure from the
point of view of you know previous
fatigues of sensuality her will and
acting out and being caught up in that
whole mess
that's why that's why in other suit as
it is said that a skillful diligent monk
should replace the um the joys of a
household life with the joys of
renunciation and that she should also replace the
and that she should also replace the
pains of a household life with the pains
of pronunciation that's why i keep
saying it needs to become your mode of
being it needs to become
your thoughts need to be by default
preferring and valuing enunciation and
giving up as opposed to sensuality and
and engagement and a household life
and you would reach the state of that
preference where you would prefer the uh
the thoughts of renunciation and as a as
your as your as your default mental
states uh through diligence so through
uh through diligence so through
diligently applying yourself not
skipping a beat in terms of
contemplating the danger of sensuality
the burden of sensuality
uh all the all the drawbacks of acting
out and giving into the pressure
certainly not gonna be developed through
the you know like doing meditation
techniques and watching your nostrils
quite the opposite you read the sutas
and we would say day and night monk a
monk purifies his mind from the
unwholesome states
so that purification of the mind it's
exactly on the level of that
contemplation of the dangers seeing how
the states have arisen how they cease
either way how they persist and how they
pressure you and not acting out of that
pressure enduring it developing a
recognition that if you haven't been acting out long
that if you haven't been acting out long
enough out of those states you will
start developing a recognition of safety
because you realize yeah it's unpleasant
it's pressuring but actually this in the
in the center of the experience of being
pressured by those that's where the
safety is so safety is you not reaching
out towards those thoughts and objects
that they present not acting out so
ironically the safety is within that
pressure but obviously habitual acting
out of pressure prevented you from ever
seeing this and that's the simile of the
of the turtle where the jackal comes and
tries to bite its limbs jackal being
mara turtle being the buddha and the
turtle just retracts all its limbs into
the shell and jacob can't do anything he
might wait and wait and wait but
eventually he'll have to give it up
because no limbs are coming out so not
reaching out it stayed within the
surrounding danger of a jackal the
turtle is actually safe
so so yes that's that's how the mind is
stilled mind is still when the danger in
those unwholesome states is sufficiently
dwelt on
for as long as it takes
not given in not not welcome not
delighted not acted out of when thoughts
of renunciation become your norm and
when your diligence
despite that fatigue of thinking
remains unchanged
so when when when you have done your
work on that level
then you will be able to afford calming
your mind within that that's what would
have said in previous suta that it's
impossible for a monk to attain the jana
unless he has fully understood the
gratification the danger and the escape
in regard to central thoughts
so so this applies the same here